M. Susan Schmidt, PhD

Beaufort, NC USA, (252) 269-0032

susu@susanschmidt.net, susankiwi15@gmail.com; www.susanschmidt.net

Developmental Editor, Author, Workshop Leader

Qualifications Summary

Dr. Schmidt's new books are *Song of Moving Water* (novel) and *Salt Runs in My Blood* (poetry). She is an Author, Editor, and Educator with 30 years experience as college and secondary teacher of literature, creative and technical writing; science policy, planning, and ethics; and 20 years as government editor and science analyst. Worldwide she edits books, and locally she leads Beaufort Writing Group. Half retired, she coaches rowing and sailing, swims, practices yoga, walks her Boykin spaniel, calls contra dances, builds community gardens. She just renewed her US Coast Guard Captain's license the seventh time (33 years). As naturalist and Quaker, Susan walks to witness natural diversity: recently Camino de Santiago, Cornwall Coastal Path, and Scottish Highlands. Won 2012 Guy Owen Poetry Prize. Published poem in *Literary Trails of Eastern NC* (2013).

Work History

Developmental Editor, Beaufort Writing Group, Beaufort, NC

January 2009 to Present

Advises authors on narrative structure; copyedits grammar and style. Edits academic/ scientific journal articles, proofreads dissertations. Edited *Beach Book, Science of the Shore*, Carl Hobbs, (Columbia University Press, 2012); *Connecting the Drops*, Karen Schneller-McDonald (Cornell UP, 2015). Quarterly, copyeditor: Harvard Business School's *Business History Review* (Cambridge UP). Edited 22 novels, including *Song of the Mokihana*, T. D. Matzenik, 1917 Pacific schooner novel; *Light on Water*, C. L. Rawlins, a New Zealand Maori saga; 20 memoirs. Leader: Writing Critique Group & workshops. Formed Kakapo Press to publish clients' books.

University Professor and Secondary Teacher

1973 to 2009

Taught university technical and creative writing, American literature, creative nonfiction, environmental literature & philosophy, science communication, conflict resolution, environmental policy & community planning, science & religion at Carteret Community College 2001-2008 & 1979-83, Hampton University 2007, Brevard College 1996-2001, Warren Wilson College 1994-95, NC School of Science & Math 1989-94, Duke University 1989-93, College of Charleston 1987-88, NC State University 1983, University of Virginia Engineering School 1979. Taught secondary literature, journalism, French, global environmental issues at SC Governor's School in Charleston 1988, Philips Academy in Andover, MA, 1989 & 1969, Collegiate School in Richmond, VA, 1973-76. Fellow at NEH Environmental Imagination Institute at Vassar, National Humanities Center, NC Center for Advancement of Teaching, Duke University Environment, Natural Resources Leadership.

Curriculum Designer, Grant-Writer, Fellowships

1976 to 2010

Wrote research grants and land-acquisition (for Nature Conservancy) topping \$5 million. Designed interdisciplinary curriculum for NC State University on humanities for engineering students, Duke University on environmental philosophy for adults and 9th-graders, Medical University of South Carolina on AIDS Education and on Medical Ethics for Family Doctors, Stratford Hall on environmental history, Christchurch School on interdisciplinary environmental Chesapeake studies, Brevard College and NC School of Science & Math on environmental humanities. Received scholarly grants from American Association of University Women on Southern Appalachian native plants & traditional music, National Endowment for the Humanities to design interdisciplinary environmental-humanities curriculum, National Science Foundation on interbasin water-transfer, Environmental Protection Agency on nonpoint-source-pollution runoff control, Office of Education for land-use/ water-quality workshops, Fulbright Foundation to teach English in West Germany. Creative-writing fellowships: VA Center for Creative Arts in VA 2000 and SW France 2008, Vermont Studio Center for fiction workshop 2006, Environmental Writing Workshop/ Montana 2000, Bread Loaf for nonfiction workshop 1999, Hambidge Center/ Georgia 1999; NC Arts Council to research Captain John Smith and Jamestown 2002.

Contract Technical Editor & Workshop Trainer

1996 to 2008

USDA Forest Service, Southern Research Station, Asheville, NC, and Atlanta, GA

Edited scientists' articles and books, including Southern Appalachian Assessment; Deerskins And Cotton, Savannah River Site before 1950; Ecology and Management, 50 Years on Savannah River Site. Led workshops (grammar, style, logic, & law) training endangered-species biologists to write legally-defensible environmental-assessment documents. Led grant-writing workshops for scientists; edited silviculture proceedings.

Environmental Scientist/ Policy Analyst/ Editor/ Mediator

1977 to 2001

For NC Natural Resources Leadership Institute mediated between NC Forest Resources & Natural Heritage to protect natural areas and wrote recreational-management plan for 12,000-acre DuPont State Forest. Mediated for Transylvania Dispute Settlement Center, Brevard, NC. Edited Environmental Science Dictionary, Bruccoli Clark. As Virginia Sea Grant Editor, VIMS, College of William & Mary, edited two monthly newsletters on commercial fishing and marine-science research. Edited *San Diego Log* (waterfront newspaper). As Environmental Scientist for NC Coastal Management, Morehead City, wrote policy reports and testified to Coastal Resources Commission on land use regulations to protect estuarine water quality, including wetland mitigation, coal ports, oil refineries; wrote grant proposal and management plan to establish NC Estuarine Research Reserve. For Nature Conservancy as steward, wrote Carrot Island Preserve Management Plan, Beaufort, NC; wrote acquisition grant and management plan for Ivy Creek Natural Area, Charlottesville, VA. For US Department of Interior, Washington, reviewed environmental-impact statements on dams, mediated among departments to write Secretary's letter.

Education

Conflict-Resolution Fellow, Natural Resources Leadership Institute, NC State University, 1998-2000 Bioethics, Environmental Philosophy Fellow, Duke University Divinity School, 1990-93 PhD, American Literature, University of South Carolina, 1990

MA, Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 1980 Watershed ecology, water quality
 Botany study, Highlands (UNC), 1996, Mt. Lake (UVa) biology stations, 1976, 1990
 MA, English, University of Virginia, 1972; Teaching License in English, Science, French, Reading (7-12th grades)
 BA, English; French, German Connecticut College, May 1971; Oxford University, England, Honors 1969-70

Publications

Dr. Schmidt is author of *Salt Runs in My Blood* (poetry) and *Song of Moving Water* (novel) (Kakapo Press, February 2015); *Landfall Along the Chesapeake, in the Wake of Captain John Smith* (Johns Hopkins UP, 2006). She published 12 poems (*Southern Poetry Review, Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina, Kakalak, ISLE, Tar River Review, Land Report*), 5 book chapters, 7 literary essays (*Shenandoah, Milkweed* anthology), 10 journal articles, 150 magazine/ newspaper articles. She edited 28 technical books, science reports & proceedings, 22 novels & 20 memoirs.

Selected Honors & Fellowships

2012 Guy Owen Poetry Prize, Poem in *Literary Trails of Eastern North Carolina* (UNC Press, 2013) VA Center for Creative Arts Fellowship SW France & VA; NC Arts Council grant Vermont Studio Center, Bread Loaf, Robert Ruark Fiction Award, NC Writers Blumenthal Reader Montana's Environmental Writing Program; Orion's Fire & Grit, Ossabaw Southern Nature Writers National Endowment for Humanities 2 Fellowships, AAUW, NSF, Fulbright

Member: Editorial Freelancers Association < http://www.the-efa.org/dir/memberinfo.php?mid=11449>
Association for Study of Literature & Environment, National Association of Science Writers,
American Association of University Women, Association of Writing Programs, Poets & Writers

Recent Travel: Scottish Highlands May 2014, Cornwall Coastal Path May 2012, Kenya Bird Survey Winter 2011.
 Walked Camino de Santiago in Spain and France 2007 & 2008. Trekked New Zealand Winters 2008 & 2010, Ireland 2006. Kayaked 500 miles NC/SC 1999, Alaska 1983. Delivered sailboats to West Indies 1980s
 Volunteer: NC Maritime Museum Junior Sailing Program; Wounded Warriors Rowing Coach, Camp Lejeune; Carteret Local Food Network, Beaufort Farmers Market, Town of Beaufort Strategic Planning Committee